are you working to a lower standard? I don't believe so, and I've always been encouraged by something that Charles Eames said. He said he was conscious of working within constraints, but not of making compromises. The distinction between a constraint and a compromise is obviously very subtle, but it's very central to my attitude to work. Remember this reading experience? The phone book. I'll hold the slide so you can enjoy the nostalgia. This is from the mid-'70s early trials of Bell Centennial typeface I designed for the U.S. phone books, and it was my first experience of digital type, and quite a baptism. Designed for the phone books, as I said, to be printed at tiny size on newsprint on very high-speed rotary presses with ink that was kerosene and lampblack. This is not a hospitable environment for a typographic designer. So the challenge for me was to design type that performed as well as possible in these very adverse production conditions. As I say, we were in the infancy of digital type. I had to draw every character by hand on quadrille graph paper -- there were four weights of Bell Centennial — pixel by pixel, then encode them raster line by raster line for the keyboard. It took two years, but I learned a lot. These letters look as though they've been chewed by the dog or something or other, but the missing pixels at the intersections of strokes or in the crotches are the result of my studying the effects of ink spread on cheap paper and reacting, revising the font accordingly. These strange artifacts are designed to compensate for the undesirable effects of scale and production process. At the outset, AT&T had wanted to set the phone books in Helvetica, but as my friend Erik Spiekermann said in the Helvetica movie, if you've seen that, the letters in Helvetica were designed to be as similar to one another as possible. This is not the recipe for legibility at small size. It looks very elegant up on a slide. I had to disambiguate these forms of the figures as much as possible in Bell Centennial by sort of opening the shapes up, as you can see in the bottom part of that slide. So now we're on to the mid-'80s, the early days of digital outline fonts, vector technology. There was an issue at that time with the size of the fonts, the amount of data that was required to find and store a font in computer memory. It limited the number of fonts you could get on your typesetting system at any one time. I did an analysis of the data, and found that a typical serif face you see on the left needed nearly twice as much data as a sans serif in the middle because of all the points required to define the elegantly curved serif brackets. The numbers at the bottom of the slide, by the way, they represent the amount of data needed to store each of the fonts. So the sans serif, in the middle, sans the serifs, was much more economical, 81 to 151. "Aha," I thought. "The engineers have a problem. Designer to the rescue." I made a serif type, you can see it on the right, without curved serifs. I made them polygonal, out of straight line segments, chamfered brackets. And look, as economical in data as a sans serif. We call it Charter, on the right. So I went to the head of engineering with my numbers, and I said proudly, "I have solved your problem." "Oh," he said. "What problem?" And I said, "Well, you know, the problem of the huge data you require for serif fonts and so on." "Oh," he said. "We solved that problem last week. We wrote a compaction routine that reduces the size of all fonts by an order of magnitude. You can have as many fonts on your system as you like." "Well, thank you for letting me know," I said. Foiled again. I was left with a design solution for a nonexistent technical problem. But here is where the story sort of gets interesting for me. I didn't just throw my design away in a fit of pique. I persevered. What had started as a technical exercise became an aesthetic exercise, really. In other words, I had come to like this typeface. Forget its origins. Screw that. I liked the design for its own sake. The simplified forms of Charter gave it a sort of plain-spoken quality and unfussy spareness that sort of pleased me. You know, at times of technical innovation, designers want to be influenced by what's in the air. We want to respond. We want to be pushed into exploring something new. So Charter is a sort of parable for me, really. In the end, there was no hard and fast causal link between the technology and the design of Charter. I had really misunderstood the technology. The technology did suggest something to me, but it did not force my hand, and I think this happens very often. You know, engineers are very smart, and despite occasional frustrations because I'm less smart, I've always enjoyed working with them and learning from them. Apropos, in the mid-'90s, I started talking to Microsoft about screen fonts. Up to that point, all the fonts on screen had been adapted from previously existing printing fonts, of course. But Microsoft foresaw correctly the movement, the stampede towards electronic communication, to reading and writing onscreen with the printed output as being sort of secondary in importance. So the priorities were just tipping at that point. They wanted a small core set of fonts that were not adapted but designed for the screen to face up to the problems of screen, which were their coarse resolution displays. I said to Microsoft, a typeface designed for a particular technology is a self-obsoleting typeface. I've designed too many faces in the past that were intended to mitigate technical problems. Thanks to the engineers, the technical problems went away. So did my typeface. It was only a stopgap. Microsoft came back to say that affordable computer monitors with better resolutions were at least a decade away. So I thought, well, a decade, that's not bad, that's more than a stopgap. So I was persuaded, I was convinced, and we went to work on what became Verdana and Georgia, for the first time working not on paper but directly onto the screen from the pixel up. At that time, screens were binary. The pixel was either on or it was off. Here you see the outline of a letter, the cap H, which is the thin black line, the contour, which is how it is stored in memory, superimposed on the bitmap, which is the grey area, which is how it's displayed on the screen. The bitmap is rasterized from the outline. Here in a cap H, which is all straight lines, the two are in almost perfect sync on the Cartesian grid. Not so with an O. This looks more like bricklaying than type design, but believe me, this is a good bitmap O, for the simple reason that it's symmetrical in both x and y axes. In a binary bitmap, you actually can't ask for more than that. I would sometimes make, I don't know, three or four different versions of a difficult letter like a lowercase A, and then stand back to choose which was the best. Well, there was no best, so the designer's judgment comes in in trying to decide which is the least bad. Is that a compromise? Not to me, if you are working at the highest standard the technology will allow, although that standard may be well short of the ideal. You may be able to see on this slide two different bitmap fonts there. The "a" in the upper one, I think, is better than the "a" in the lower one, but it still ain't great. You can maybe see the effect better if it's reduced. Well, maybe not. So I'm a pragmatist, not an idealist, out of necessity. For a certain kind of temperament, there is a certain kind of satisfaction in doing something that cannot be perfect but can still be done to the best of your ability. Here's the lowercase H from Georgia Italic. The bitmap looks jagged and rough. It is jagged and rough. But I discovered, by experiment, that there is an optimum slant for an italic on a screen so the strokes break well at the pixel boundaries. Look in this example how, rough as it is, how the left and right legs actually break at the same level. That's a victory. That's good, right there. And of course, at the lower depths, you don't get much choice. This is an S, in case you were wondering. Well, it's been 18 years now since Verdana and Georgia were released. Microsoft were absolutely right, it took a good 10 years, but screen displays now do have improved spatial resolution, and very much improved photometric resolution thanks to anti-aliasing and so on. So now that their mission is accomplished, has that meant the demise of the screen fonts that I designed for coarser displays back then? Will they outlive the now-obsolete screens and the flood of new web fonts coming on to the market? Or have they established their own sort of evolutionary niche that is independent of technology? In other words, have they been absorbed into the typographic mainstream? I'm not sure, but they've had a good run so far. Hey, 18 is a good age for anything with present-day rates of attrition, so I'm not complaining. Thank you. (Applause)
produisez-vous un travail de moins bonne qualité ? Je ne le pense pas, et les propos de Charles Eames déclarant qu'il avait conscience d'être dans la contrainte, mais pas dans le compromis, m'ont toujours encouragé. Il est vrai que la distinction entre une contrainte et un compromis est très subtile, mais elle est au cœur de mon attitude face au travail. Vous vous souvenez de ça ? L'annuaire. Je la laisse pour la séquence nostalgie. Ce sont les premiers essais, au milieu des années 1970, de la police Bell Centennial que j'ai créée pour les annuaires américains, c'était ma première expérience de police numérique, et un sacré baptême. Destinée, donc, aux annuaires, pour être imprimée à une taille minuscule sur du papier journal par des presses à rotatives ultra-rapides avec une encre au kérosène et à la suie. Ce n'est pas un environnement hospitalier pour un concepteur de typographie. Le défi fut donc de créer la police qui conviendrait le mieux à ces terribles conditions de production. C'était les prémices de la typographie numérique. Je devais dessiner tous les caractères à la main sur du papier millimétré - Bell Centennial existait en 4 graisses - pixel par pixel, puis les encoder trame par trame pour le clavier. Cela a pris 2 ans, mais j'ai énormément appris. Ces lettres ont l'air mâchées par le chien ou autre, mais les pixels évidés aux intersections des fûts ou aux angles sont le résultat de mon observation de l'influence de l'encre imprimée sur du papier bon marché et de ma réaction en adaptant la police. Ces étranges pattes de mouches sont conçues pour compenser les effets indésirables de l'échelle et des procédés de production. Au départ, AT&T voulait imprimer ses annuaires en Helvetica, mais, comme Erik Spiekermann le dit dans le film Helvetica, si vous l'avez vu, les lettres Helvetica ont été conçues pour favoriser au maximum la similitude entre elles. Ce n'est pas un bon choix pour une lisibilité en petite taille. C'est très élégant sur une diapositive. J'ai dû différencier les formes de ces chiffres autant que possible pour Bell Centennial en ouvrant les formes de cette façon, ainsi, en bas de cette diapositive. A présent, nous arrivons au milieu des années 1980, les premiers jours des polices numériques détourées, la technologie vectorielle. A cette époque, il y avait un problème de taille des polices de caractères, et de quantité de données nécessaires pour trouver et stocker une police dans la mémoire d'un ordinateur. Le nombre de polices disponibles dans votre programme typographique était limité. J'ai procédé à une analyse des données, et découvert qu'une police serif typique que vous voyez à gauche représentait presque le double de données qu'une sans serif, au milieu, à cause de tous les points nécessaires pour dessiner les courbes élégantes des angles d'empattements de la serif. D'ailleurs, les chiffres en bas de la diapositive représentent la quantité de données nécessaires au stockage de chacune des polices. Donc, la sans serif, au milieu, sans empattements, était beaucoup plus économique, à 81 pour 151. Je me suis dit : « Ah ah ! Les ingénieurs ont un problème. Appelons le concepteur à la rescousse ! » J'ai créé une police serif, à droite, sans empattements arrondis. Ils sont polygonaux, faits de segments de droites, et d'angles chanfreinés. Et voilà, aussi économe de données que la sans serif. Elle se nomme Charter, à droite. J'ai présenté au chef des ingénieurs mes chiffres, et j'ai déclaré fièrement : « J'ai résolu votre problème. » Il a répondu : « Ah ? Quel problème ? » Moi : « Eh bien, vous savez, celui de l'énorme quantité de données nécessaires aux polices serif. » Il a dit : « Oh ! On a résolu ça la semaine dernière, avec une routine de compactage qui réduit la taille des polices par un ordre de magnitude. Toutes les polices que vous voulez sont dans le système. » J'ai dit : « Eh bien, merci pour l'information. » Encore raté ! J'avais sur les bras une solution pour un problème technique inexistant. Mais c'est là que l'histoire devient intéressante. Je n'ai pas jeté mes dessins dans un accès de déception. J'ai persévéré. Ce qui avait débuté en exercice technique était devenu un exercice esthétique, vraiment. Autrement dit, j'en étais venu à aimer cette police. Peu importe ses origines. On s'en fiche. J'aimais ce dessin pour lui-même. Les formes simplifiées de Charter lui conféraient une qualité évidente et une retenue sobre qui me ravissaient. Vous savez, à une époque d'innovations technologiques les concepteurs veulent être influencés par l'air du temps. Nous voulons réagir. Nous voulons être poussés dans l'exploration de la nouveauté. Charter est vraiment une parabole pour moi. En réalité, il n'y a pas eu de lien tangible et immédiat entre la technologie et la conception de Charter. Je n'avais vraiment pas compris la technologie. Elle m'a bien suggéré quelque chose, mais elle ne m'a pas forcé la main, et je crois que cela arrive très souvent. Vous savez, les ingénieurs sont très intelligents, et malgré quelques frustrations car je suis moins intelligent, j'ai toujours apprécié travailler avec eux et apprendre d'eux. A propos, au milieu des années 1990, j'ai commencé à parler à Microsoft des polices d'écran. Jusque là, toutes les polices pour écran avaient été adaptées de polices d'impression existantes, naturellement. Mais Microsoft avait bien anticipé le mouvement, la ruée vers les communications électroniques, vers la lecture et l'écriture sur écran reléguant l'imprimé au second rang en importance. A ce moment, les priorités n'étaient qu'émergentes. Ils voulaient un petit ensemble de base de polices, non pas adaptées, mais conçues pour l'écran pour contrer son problème : la résolution grossière de l'affichage. J'ai averti Microsoft qu'une police conçue pour une technologie particulière était une police à l'obsolescence programmée. J'avais déjà conçu trop de polices dans le but de remédier à des problèmes techniques. Grâce aux ingénieurs, les problèmes disparaissaient. Ainsi que ma police. Ce n'était qu'un palliatif. Microsoft a répondu que les moniteurs d'un prix abordable à meilleure résolution n'apparaîtraient pas avant une dizaine d'années. J'ai pensé alors : 10 ans, c'est pas si mal, c'est mieux que du palliatif. Donc, j'étais persuadé, convaincu, et nous avons créé ce qui allait être Verdana et Georgia, pour la première fois, travaillant non sur papier mais directement sur écran, à partir du pixel. A cette époque, les écrans étaient binaires. Le pixel était soit "on" soit "off". Voici le contour d'une lettre, le H majuscule, c'est la fine ligne noire, le contour, qui est le moyen de le conserver dans la mémoire, superposé à l'image numérique, la zone grise, qui est ce qui apparaît sur l'écran. L'image numérique est tramée à partir du contour. Avec un H majuscule, fait de lignes droites, tout est quasiment parfaitement synchronisé dans le système de coordonnées cartésiennes. Pour le O, c'est une autre histoire. C'est plus de la maçonnerie que de la typographie, mais croyez-moi, c'est un bon O en image numérique, pour la simple raison qu'il est symétrique à la fois sur l'axe x et sur l'axe y. Pour une image numérique binaire, on ne peut pas demander mieux, en réalité. Il m'est arrivé de concevoir, je ne sais pas, 3 ou 4 versions d'une lettre difficile comme un « a » minuscule, et de prendre du recul pour choisir la meilleure. Mais, il n'y en avait pas, alors le jugement du concepteur intervient pour tenter de décider laquelle est la moins mauvaise. Est-ce un compromis ? Pas pour moi, si vous travaillez au meilleur de ce que la technologie vous permet, bien que ce meilleur soit loin de l'idéal. Vous voyez sur cette diapositive 2 polices numériques différentes. Je pense que le « a » en haut est meilleur que le « a » en bas, mais ce n'est toujours pas génial. Vous pourrez mieux voir l'effet si c'est réduit. Ou pas. Je suis donc un pragmatique, pas un idéaliste, par nécessité. Pour certains tempéraments, il y a une espèce de satisfaction à faire quelque chose qui ne peut être parfait mais qui peut être fait au meilleur de leurs possibilités. Voici le H minuscule en Georgia italique. L'image a l'air dentelée et grossière. Elle l'est. Mais j'ai découvert, avec l'expérience, qu'il y a une inclinaison optimale pour l'italique à l'écran donc les fûts sont bien divisés aux limites des pixels. Regardez dans cet exemple, aussi grossier soit-il, comment les branches droite et gauche se divisent au même niveau. C'est une victoire. Là, c'est bien. Et bien sûr, aux plus basses résolutions, vous n'avez pas vraiment le choix. C'est un S, au cas où vous en doutiez. Alors, cela fait 18 ans maintenant que Verdana et Georgia sont sorties. Microsoft avait complètement raison, cela a pris 10 bonnes années, mais la résolution spatiale des écrans a bien été améliorée, et la résolution photométrique encore plus grâce notamment à l'anticrénelage. Donc, à présent que leur mission est accomplie, est-ce la fin des polices que j'avais conçues à l'époque pour des écrans moins précis ? Vont-elles survivre à ces vieux écrans et au flot de nouvelles polices Web apparaissant sur le marché ? Ou ont-elles établi leur propre niche d'évolution indépendante de la technologie ? Ou alors, ont-elles été absorbées par la tendance typographique dominante ? Je n'en suis pas sûr, mais elles ont bien tenu le coup. 18 ans est un bon âge pour n'importe quoi avec les taux d'usure actuels, je n'ai pas à me plaindre. Merci. (Applaudissements)